Finding Aid for Karl Pohrt papers, 1948-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Karl Pohrt papers 1976-2013
Pohrt, Karl, 1948-2013
241 MB online
1 oversize folder
3.5 linear feet including oversize
2014105 Aa 2 UAl
Owner and operator of the Shaman Drum Bookshop, a noted independent bookstore in Ann Arbor, Mich. that gained national recognition and regularly hosted leading contemporary American writers from 1981 until its closure in 2009. Collection includes business records, articles about the bookselling industry, press coverage, photographs, printed broadsides, catalogs, store newsletters and posters documenting events at the Shaman Drum. Also contains records of Pohrt's other business affiliations and involvement in local cultural initiatives such as the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair and the Ann Arbor Book Festival.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Dianne Pohrt (donor no. 11112 ) in May, 2014.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Karl Weidner Pohrt is perhaps best known as the owner of the Shaman Drum, an independent bookstore in Ann Arbor, yet he was also a poet, activist, teacher, scholar and publisher. An accomplished scholar of American 'Beat Generation' literature and practicing Buddhist, Pohrt was also a longtime friend of the poet Gary Snyder. Pohrt was born in 1948 in Flint, Michigan. His farther Richard Pohrt was a noted collector of Native American art and artifacts. After earning his bachelor's degree in English at the University of Michigan-Flint in 1970, Pohrt worked at St. Joseph Mercy Hospital in Ann Arbor to fulfill his service obligation as a conscientious objector to the Vietnam War. He then worked as a bookseller at Centicore Books, a bookstore in Ann Arbor in the early seventies, before finishing a master's degree in American Culture at the University of Michigan in 1978. While working on his master's degree, Pohrt helped establish the Bear Claw Press in Ann Arbor with his brother, artist and illustrator Tom Pohrt. Karl Pohrt also worked as a writing instructor in the 1970s and taught English and composition as an adjunct at the University of Michigan Flint in 1980. He left teaching to open an independent bookstore on State Street in Ann Arbor in 1981.
The Shaman Drum Bookshop went on to become a nationally recognized bookstore as well as a central gathering place for the community of arts and letters in Ann Arbor. Despite the rise of online booksellers, textbook sales helped keep Pohrt's business financially sustainable. Pohrt cultivated a niche for readers interested in scholarly and academic literature, while maintaining a welcoming atmosphere attractive to the Ann Arbor community at large. Located at 311 S State Street in downtown Ann Arbor, Shaman Drum's proximity to the University's Central Campus also helped strengthen town-gown relations.
Pohrt served several terms as the president of the American Bookseller's Association. In addition, Pohrt was a board member for the Ann Arbor Downtown Development Authority and State Street Association. He also served as the president of the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair in 2006 and helped with the founding of the first Ann Arbor Book Festival in 2003. Pohrt helped co-found an initiative known as "Reading the World" in 2005, inviting independent booksellers and publishers nationwide to display foreign literature published in translation each year through the month of May. In 2006, George Eley, a University of Michigan professor of German history, received a distinguished professorship and named it for Karl Pohrt, becoming the Karl Pohrt Distinguished University Professor of Contemporary History. Eley explained he wanted to honor Pohrt's commitment to promoting the humanities and higher education in Ann Arbor to help improve the political, social, and cultural life of the city.
Despite the success and the reputation of the Shaman Drum as a center for cultural and intellectual gatherings in Ann Arbor, increased competition with online booksellers and other forms of digital publication during the economic recession resulted in a steep and sudden decline in sales at the Shaman Drum, pushing Pohrt to dramatically adjust the store's mission and strategic plan. In February 2008, Pohrt announced that he would transform his privately owned store into a nonprofit literary arts center. With this transition, Pohrt intended to expand the shop's community programming from poetry readings, book signings, and literary receptions to offer courses in literature and creative writing. He opened the Great Lakes Literary Arts Center at the Shaman Drum Bookshop in the summer of 2008. Nevertheless, the combined forces of the recession and continuing competition with online retailers and Internet media ultimately took their toll on the Shaman Drum. Pohrt closed the Shaman Drum in June 2009.
After closing down his business, Pohrt continued to write about books, culture and ideas in his personal blog. Pohrt was diagnosed with cancer in October 2012 and continued to publish his blog until May 2013. He died on July 10, 2013 and was survived by his wife, Diane, and two daughters.
The collection is divided into four series: Shaman Drum Bookshop, Other Business Affiliations and Community Initiatives, Teaching and Research, and Personal Files.
The Karl Pohrt papers consist of materials relating to Pohrt's personal life, education, teaching, business ventures, and involvement in professional associations and community initiatives. Photographs, personal writings, signed broadsides, and correspondence document Pohrt's contact and friendships with writers and academics. In addition, the Pohrt papers include press articles and documentation from meetings providing a view into the effects of online retail on the bookselling industry.
Subjects:
Bear Claw Press.; Book industries and trade--United States.; Bookstores--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Festivals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Independent bookstores--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Indians of North America--Folklore.; Pohrt, Karl 1948-2013.; Publishers and publishing--United States.; Shaman Drum Bookshop.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bookstores.; Writers.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
corpname; persname; geogname
Contributors:
Pohrt, Richard A., 1911-2005.; Snyder, Gary, 1930-
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; Digital file formats.; Floor plans.; Portraits.; Posters.
- Shaman Drum Bookshop
  - Operational materials
    The Shaman Drum Bookshop series (2.2 linear feet, 1980-2009) consists of seven groups: Operational materials, Promotional materials, Community outreach, Literary posters and broadsides, Writings, Photographs, and the Great Lakes Literary Arts Center at the Shaman Drum. In addition to these seven groups, this series contains a Special Issue of Michigan Quarterly Review, which features a symposium discussing the future of books and reading in the digital age in response to the closure of the Shaman Drum. Operational materials include strategic plans, policies, vision and values statements, meeting materials, memoranda, professional correspondence, inventories, and floor plans for the 1994 expansion of the shop. Promotional materials encompass press articles, event flyers and posters, and store newsletters and catalogs. Community outreach materials consist of speeches, honors, advocacy videos and writings, and store anniversary memorabilia. The literary posters and broadsides group contains materials with autographs and notes from writers. Writings consist of Pohrt's personal reflections, presentations and blog posts. Photographs document store transformations, store sponsored events and visits from writers and academics. The Great Lakes Literary Arts Center group contains records relating to the transformation of the Shaman Drum from a private business to a nonprofit literary arts center.
    - Vision, values, strategic plans and policies, circa 1993-2003 (Box 1)
    - Meeting agendas and minutes, 1994-2002 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda, 1993-2005 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1994-2006 (Box 1)
    - Textbook inventories, 1989-1992, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Floor plans, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Promotional materials
    - Press coverage, 1989-2008 (Box 1)
    - Flyers, bookmarks, and signs, circa 1990-1999, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Shaman Drum newsletters and notices, 1995-2009 (Box 1)
    - Shaman Drum catalogs, 1997-2008, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Posters, 2005-2008 (Box 4)
  - Community outreach
    - Anniversaries and events, 2001-2009 (Box 1)
      (Includes introductory speech for Bill Ayers' visit in 2009)
    - Certificate of Appreciation from University of Michigan, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Advocacy
      - Video recordings, 2009, .ZIP and .MP4 files
      - Writings, 2009-2010, .ZIP file
  - Literary posters and broadsides
    - Circa 1969-1991 (Box 1)
      (Includes posters signed by Czeslaw Milosz and Clayton Eshleman)
    - Circa 1969-1991 (Box 4)
      (Includes posters signed by Gary Snyder, Clayton Eshleman, and Wendell Berry)
  - Writings
    - Printed blog, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Reflections, presentations, and projects, undated (Box 1)
      (Includes sketches)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits of writers, undated (Box 1)
    - Store views and collages, circa 1994 (Box 1)
      (Includes photograph of Pohrt with Allen Ginsberg and Ken Mikolowski)
    - Miscellaneous photographs of staff and store events, undated (Box 4)
    - Customers and employees, undated (Box 3)
    - Visiting Writers and Events
      - Gary Snyder, 1995, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Jamaica Kincaid, 1996 (Box 3)
      - Clayton Eshleman, 1996 (Box 3)
      - Janet Kauffman Graywolf and Nelson Lichtenstein, 1996 (Box 3)
      - Poets on Poems, 1996 (Box 3)
      - Author signings, undated (Box 3)
      - Blocksma, Sanders, Achenbaum, Hicok, undated (Box 3)
      - Manning Marable and Johnson, undated (Box 3)
      - Marcus Cafagna and Jean Craighead George, 1996 (Box 3)
      - Barbara Ehrenreich, undated (Box 3)
      - Boychoir, Hayden. Dyson, 1996 (Box 3)
      - Banned Books and Jim Daniels, 1996 (Box 3)
      - Talalay, Goodison, and Cormier, undated (Box 3)
      - Allen Ginsberg and Patti Smith, 1996 (Box 3)
      - Laura Kasischke, Allen Ginsberg, Patti Smith, undated (Box 3)
      - Margaret Wong, undated (Box 3)
    - Reading the World reception, 2006, .ZIP file
      Event hosted by French Embassy in Washington, DC
    - Photograph Albums
      - Building the Drum, 1994 (Box 2)
      - The Early Years, circa 1994 (Box 3)
      - Untitled, circa 1995 (Box 3)
  - Great Lakes Literary Arts Center at the Shaman Drum, 2008-2009 (Box 1)
  - Special Issue of Michigan Quarterly Review, 2009 (Box 1)
    Features Symposium on the future of books in the digital age in response to the closing of the Shaman Drum
- Other Business Affiliations and Community Initiatives
  The Other Business Affiliations and Community Initiatives series (0.2 linear feet, 1976-2007) is divided according to organization or initiative into six groups: the Bear Claw Press, the American Booksellers' Association, the Independent Booksellers' Consortium, the Ann Arbor Book Festival, the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair and Democratic primary for Ann Arbor City Council. The Bear Claw Press group contains original calendars, correspondence, and photographic materials. The American Booksellers' Association group consists of correspondence and event programming schedules. The Independent Booksellers' Consortium group includes documentation from meetings, a directory of member organizations, and an undated proposal for a coalition of independent booksellers written by Pohrt. The Ann Arbor Book Festival and Ann Arbor Street Art Fair groups contain board meeting minutes and financial records; the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair group also includes bylaws and photographs. Democratic primary for Ann Arbor City Council contains a campaign sign from Pohrt's run to be nominated as a candidate for the City Council election in 2002.
  - Bear Claw Press
    - Print materials, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      (Includes negative and photograph from Richard A. Pohrt's personal collection used in publishing Jim Heynen's poetry collection, Notes for Custer)
    - Calendar, 1977 (Box 4)
  - American Booksellers' Association, 2002-2005 (Box 1)
    Includes photograph and letter signed by first lady Laura Bush
  - Independent Booksellers' Consortium
    - Proposed model for coalition and directory, undated (Box 1)
    - General Managers' meeting, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Idea Exchange, 2004 and 2007, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor Book Festival
    - Administrative materials and press coverage, 2004-2007 (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 2004, .ZIP file
  - Ann Arbor Street Art Fair, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Campaign Sign for Ann Arbor City Council Democratic Primary, 2002, .ZIP file
- Teaching and Research
  The Teaching and Research series (0.4 linear feet, 1970-1980) consists of two groups: the University of Michigan Flint and Native American literature. The University of Michigan Flint group contains syllabi, lesson plans, lecture notes, assignments, and some samples of student writing. The Native American literature group includes syllabi, lecture notes, and a sample of Pohrt's academic writing.
  - University of Michigan Flint, 1970-1980
    - Memorabilia and notes, circa 1970 (Box 2)
    - Lectures and notes for English 101, 1980
      - Introduction (Box 2)
      - Prewriting (Box 2)
      - Commitment and response (Box 2)
      - The writer's voice (Box 2)
      - Description and specificity (Box 2)
      - Analysis and classification (Box 2)
      - Review and student conferences (Box 2)
      - Sentence and paragraph structure (Box 2)
      - Explicitness, Relationships, Predication (Box 2)
      - Logic (Box 2)
        (Includes student reflection on poetry reading by Joseph Brodsky at U of M Flint)
      - Style (Box 2)
      - Introduction to research techniques (Box 2)
      - Review and final student conferences (Box 2)
  - Native American literature, undated (Box 2)
    (Includes notes on oral literature and ethnogeography)
- Personal Files
  The Personal Files series (0.6 linear feet, 1968-2013) is divided into seven groupings: Correspondence, Photographs and portraits, Writings and original art, Education, Community recognition, Travels, and Topical files. Correspondence consists of incoming letters. The Photographs and portraits group contains images of Pohrt. The Writings and original art group includes poetry, essays, blogs, interviews and articles written by Pohrt as well as writing and art by Pohrt's friends and prints by the Alternative Press in Detroit. The Education group consists of Pohrt's diplomas. The Community recognition group contains individual honors granted to Pohrt, including a Special Tribute from the State of Michigan. The Travels group consists of personal writings and travel diaries, brochures, maps, memorabilia, itineraries and photographic slides from Pohrt's travels in Nicaragua, Mexico, India, and France. Topical files document Pohrt's longstanding interests in world history, Buddhism, and the cultural heritage of indigenous peoples of North America.
  - Correspondence
    - 1968-2013 with gaps, 4 folders (Box 2)
      (Includes correspondence with Gary Snyder)
    - 2010-2013, .ZIP file
  - Photographs and portraits, circa 1994-2000 (Box 2)
    (Includes caricature)
  - Writings and original art
    - Essays by Pohrt, circa 2008-2009 (Box 2)
    - Poetry by Pohrt
      - 1979 (Box 2)
      - 2011, .ZIP file
    - Blogs and reflections by Pohrt, 2000-2013, .ZIP file
    - Eulogy and obituary, 2010-2013, .ZIP file; ( Includes eulogy for Pohrt by George Eley and an obituary for Pohrt's mother, Marion Dena Pohrt)
    - Interviews and articles by Pohrt, 2009-2012, .ZIP file
    - Poetry by others, 1976-1999 with gaps (Box 2)
    - Poetry printed by the Alternative Press, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - First meeting with Gary Snyder
      - Autobiographical essay by Pohrt, 1975 (Box 2)
      - Photographs, 1975, .ZIP file
    - Watercolors, undated (Box 4)
  - Education
    - High school, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Bachelor's degree, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Master's degree, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Community recognition
    - Honors and resolution, 2001-2008 with gaps (Box 2)
    - State of Michigan Special Tribute, 2008 (Box 4)
  - Travels (Box 2)
    - Nicaragua journals, 2011-2012, .ZIP file
    - Mexico, 2010, .ZIP file
    - Mexico, undated (Box 2)
    - India, 1991 (Box 2)
    - France
      (Trip to Southern France to see cave art with Clayton and Caryl Eshleman and Gary and Carole Snyder)
      - Itinerary, 1996 (Box 2)
      - Photographic slides, 1996, 1 box; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Topical files (Box 2)
    - World history, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Native Alaskans, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Buddhism, circa 1987 (Box 2)
    - Native American culture, 1975-1991
      - Poster for cultural workshop, 1975 (Box 4)
      - Print materials, poetry and graphics, circa 1991 (Box 2)
      - Audio recording of Richard Pohrt on Native American tales, undated, 1 audiocassette (Box 3)
Related Materials
The Special Collections Library at the University of Michigan houses a collection of copies of Byblio, the Shaman Drum newsletter (see http://mirlyn.lib.umich.edu/Record/012630837/).